<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="64"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Introduction to India’s Criminal Justice System










  • The Criminal Justice System of any state is the set of agencies and processes
      established by governments for administration of criminal justice aimed at

      controlling crime and imposing punishment on persons who violate the law.

  • The Union of India - Federal State consisting: Central government and the State

      governments in the twenty nine states.

  • The states have their own powers and functioning under the Constitution of India.


  • Police and Prison - the state subjects.


  • Federal laws - followed by the Police, Judiciary, and Correctional Institutes.

  • Dispensation of criminal justice in India follows Adversarial system of common

      law inherited from the British Colonial Rulers.

  • In the Indian CJS, the Police investigate, while the Judge's role is like a neutral

      umpire and a fact finder and he also imposes the sentence.


  • The execution of the sentence is bestowed on the Correctional institutes.

  • CJS – based on IPC: enacted in 1860.


  • CJS also ensures that those accused of criminal activities are treated fairly and are
      given their due rights.]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Composition of Criminal Justice System







  • The criminal justice system in India is composed of three main components:

                 I.       Police

                 II.      Judiciary

                 III.     Correctional System


  • ‘Prevention and control of crime’ - Criminal Justice System: involves the process of arrest, trial, conviction, sentencing,

      punishment/treatment and finally rehabilitation.

  • The legislature is also an important component of the Criminal Justice System, as all the laws emanate from the floor of the

      legislature.

  • The courts interpret the laws and police is the executing agency.


  • The structure of Criminal Justice system consists of the four main pillars namely:

                 1. Investigation by Police,

                 2. Prosecution of case by the Prosecutors,

                 3. determination of guilt by the Courts and

                 4. finally the correction through prisons system.]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[1. Investigation by Police:

  • crux of the Criminal trial - investigation done by the police.


  • The police are the first point of contact for those affected by crime, and are responsible for collecting evidence and
      apprehending criminals.

  • Under Section 161 (CrPC) - information of the offence is registered in the local police station.


  • Under Section 156 (CrPC) - police starts the investigation.

  • Under Section 161 (CrPC) – empowers the IO to examine any person supposed to be acquainted with the facts and
      circumstances of the case and record the statement in writing.


  • Under Section 162 (CrPC) – only the accused that can make use of such a statement.

  • Any confession made by the accused before the Police officer is not admissible and cannot be made use of during the trial of
      the case.


  • The statement of the accused recorded by the police can be used as provided under Section 27 of the Evidence Act to the
      limited extent that led to the discovery of any fact.

  • Under Section 41 (CrPC) – Arrest of any person by police in case of Cognizable offence.


  • Section 46 (CrPC) – Procedure of arrest.

  • Section 165 &166 (CrPC) – Police can search any area or premise where there is any chance of getting any evidence
      (documents, materials) in relation to cognizable act.


  • Section 102 (CrPC) – Any such item may be seized by police

  • Section 164 (CrPC) - Police has the discretion to discharge a person arrested on executing a bond.


  • Section 173 (Cr PC) - statements of the witnesses, and the evidence collected through the investigation along with the copy of
      the First Information Report is made into a Police report and submitted to Magistrate.]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[POLICE ORGANIZATION



  • The police is a state subject and its organization and working are governed

      by rules and regulations framed by the state governments.

  • Police Manuals of the state police forces – Rules and regulations outlined.


  • Each State/Union Territory has its separate police force.


  • Despite the diversity of police forces, there is a good deal that is common
      amongst them. This is due to four main reasons:


  1. The structure and working of the State Police Forces are governed by
        the Police Act of 1861, which is applicable in most parts of the country, or

        by the State Police Acts modeled mostly on the 1861 legislation.

  2.     The Indian Police Service (IPS) is an All India Service, which is

        recruited, trained and managed by the Central Government and which
        provides the bulk of senior officers to the State Police Forces.


  3. The quasi-federal character of the Indian polity, with specific provisions
        in the Constitution, allows a coordinating and counseling role for the

        Centre in police matters and even authorizes it to set up certain central
        police organizations (Commonwealth Human Rights Initiatives, 2001).


  4. Superintendence over the police force in the state is exercised by the State
        Government (Section 3, The Police Act, 1861).]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[• Cont..

  • Director General of Police (DGP) - head of the police force in the state; responsible for the administration of the police force
      in the state and for advising the government on police matters.


  • Field Establishment States are divided territorially into administrative units known as districts.


  • Superintendent of Police (SP) - officer of the rank of SP heads the district police force.


  • Deputy Inspector General (DIG) of Police - A group of districts form a range, which is looked after by an officer of the rank
      of DIG.


  • Inspector General (IG) of Police - Some states have zones comprising two or more ranges and they are under the charge of
      an officer of the rank of an IG.


  • Asst. Superintendent of Police/ Dy. Superintendent of Police (ASP/Dy.SP) - Every district is divided into sub-divisions. A
      sub-division is under the charge of an officer of the rank of ASP/ Dy.S.P.


  • Inspector of Police (PI) - Every sub-division is further divided into a number of police stations, depending on its area,
      population and volume of crime. Between the police station and the subdivision, there are police circles in some states each

      circle headed generally by an Inspector of Police.

  • The police station is the basic unit of police administration in a district.


  • Under the Criminal Procedure Code, all crime has to be recorded at the police station and all preventive, investigative and
      law and order work is done from there.


  • A police station is divided into a number of beats, which are assigned to constables for patrolling, surveillance, collection of

      intelligence, etc.

  • The officer in charge of a police station is an Inspector of Police, particularly in cities and metropolitan areas.


  • In rural areas or smaller police stations, the officer in charge is usually a Sub-Inspector of Police (PSI).]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[What is the Police Commissionerates System?








   This system essentially splits a district in two parts from the point of view


       of policing.

   The part of the city that forms the large urbanized settlement becomes a


       geographical          area      where       the     police      responsibilities        of    District


       Superintendent of Police get transferred to the Commissioner of Police.


   Along with this, the powers of the District Magistrate (DM), the Sub-


       divisional Magistrates (SDM) and the Executive Magistrates in the area of

       crime and law and order also get transferred to the Police Commissioner.


   For the rest of the District, however, both the District Magistrate, his


       subordinate magistrates and the District Superintendent of Police retain


       their police powers.


   responsibility for policing the city/area is vested on the Commissioner of


       Police; introduced in metropolitan areas like Calcutta, Bombay, Madras

       and Hyderabad;]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[• Criminal               Investigation              Department                 (CID)          -

       specialized branches of the police force; two main

       components - the Crime Branch and the Special

       Branch; investigates specialized crimes - counterfeiting

       of currency, professional cheating, activities of

       criminal gangs, crimes with interdistrict or inter-state

       ramifications etc.



















   • Central Bureau of Investigation (CBI) - Initially used

       to known as Special Police Establishment (SPE) in

       1941 to investigate cases of bribery and corruption

       involving the employees of the War and Supply

       Department of the Government of India during the

       Second          World         War;        The       Delhi        Special         Police

       Establishment Act was passed in 1946 to give the

       organization a statutory base.]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[2. Role of Prosecutor:

  • crux of the Criminal trial - investigation done by the police.


  • The police are the first point of contact for those affected by crime, and are responsible for collecting evidence and
      apprehending criminals.

  • Under Section 161 (CrPC) - information of the offence is registered in the local police station.


  • Under Section 156 (CrPC) - police starts the investigation.

  • Under Section 161 (CrPC) – empowers the IO to examine any person supposed to be acquainted with the facts and
      circumstances of the case and record the statement in writing.


  • Under Section 162 (CrPC) – only the accused that can make use of such a statement.

  • Any confession made by the accused before the Police officer is not admissible and cannot be made use of during the trial of
      the case.


  • The statement of the accused recorded by the police can be used as provided under Section 27 of the Evidence Act to the
      limited extent that led to the discovery of any fact.

  • Under Section 41 (CrPC) – Arrest of any person by police in case of Cognizable offence.


  • Section 46 (CrPC) – Procedure of arrest.

  • Section 165 &166 (CrPC) – Police can search any area or premise where there is any chance of getting any evidence
      (documents, materials) in relation to cognizable act.


  • Section 102 (CrPC) – Any such item may be seized by police

  • Section 164 (CrPC) - Police has the discretion to discharge a person arrested on executing a bond.


  • Section 173 (Cr PC) - statements of the witnesses, and the evidence collected through the investigation along with the copy of
      the First Information Report is made into a Police report and submitted to Magistrate.]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[3. Judiciary:







  • The judiciary is responsible for making sure that trials are conducted fairly and that justice is

      served.


  • Judges preside over criminal trials and make sure that the accused are given their due rights.



  • Sec 190 (CrPC):  role of the judge or the Court in India starts from the stage of taking

      cognizance of the criminal case under this section.



  • Sec 192 (CrPC): making over of the case to the appropriate court having jurisdiction to try the

      case.


  • Sec 204 (CrPC): issue of process either by summons or warrant as the case may be.



  • During the whole process of trial the court’s duty is finding of the facts that are relevant from

      the evidence presented by the prosecutor and the defense and come to the conclusion of the guilt

      by making a balance sheet of the aggravating and mitigating factors.]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Legislative process in criminal justice system







  • The legislature is that organ of the government which passes the laws of the government. Legislature may be of two
      types :- Unicameral or Bicameral.


  • Unicameralism: A system in which there is only one House of the Legislature.

  • Bicameralism: When there are two Houses of the Legislature.


  • The term ‘legislature’ is a generic term meaning a body which legislates.


  • Legislature or Parliament is that branch of government which performs the function of lawmaking through
      deliberations.


  • The term ‘ Legg means law and “lature’   the place and etymologically Legislature means a place for law-making.
      Another term, which is used as a synonym of Legislature, is ‘Parliament.’


  • It is the agency which has the responsibility to formulate the will of the state and vest it with legal authority and
      force.


  • The legislature is that organ of the government which formulates laws.

  • Legislature enjoys a very special and important in every democratic state.


  • This word stands derived from the French word ‘Parley’ which means to ‘talk’ or to discuss and deliberate.
      ‘Parliament’ means the place where deliberations are held.


  • It is the assembly of the elected representatives of the people and represents national public opinion and power
      of the people.]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Adversarial and Inquisitorial Systems



  • Adversarial system:

           a system where the court act as a referee between the prosecution and the defense.

           The whole process is a contest between two parties.
           As regard crime these two parties are the state & the person accused .

           In this process court takes a non partisan role.

           This system followed in all those countries that follow common law inherited from the British Colonial Rulers.

           It advocates the supremacy of law, that is, equal treatment of law for all segments of society.

           Accused is presumed to be innocent and the burden is on the prosecution to prove beyond all reasonable doubt and if there
             is any doubt, the benefit of doubt goes in favor of accused.

           The accused also enjoys the right to silence and cannot be compelled to reply. This right is guaranteed by Constitution of
             India in the form of fundamental right and also a universally recognized right of the accused.






  • Inquisitorial system:

           a legal system where the court is actively involved in proof of facts by taking investigating of the case.

           This system resolving disputes and achieving justice for individuals and society.

           The inquisitorial model basically relates to Romano Germanic System of Law, which is also known as civil law system or
             continental law system.

           This system tends to treat the court, police and prosecution as parties to crime or partners in quest for truth or justice.

           It aims to attain justice with the composite effort of the prosecutor, the police, the defense lawyer and the court.
           The court can play active role in procuring evidence, in the investigation of the case and the examination of the witness]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Fundamental elements in judicial functioning









  1. DUE PROCESS OF LAW:







          • Due process acts as a check on arbitrary use of power and protects individuals.


          • The regular administration of the law, according to which no individual may be denied their legal rights
             and all laws must conform to fundamental, accepted legal principles, such of the accused to confront their

             accusers. as the right

          • Due process ensures that all legal rules and principles about a case are applied by the state, protecting the

             legal rights of the individual.

          • An example of due process is ensuring a person who was caught red-handed robbing a bank must still go to

             court and have the chance to be represented by a lawyer rather than being sent straight to prison.

          • It balances the power of the law and protects individuals from it. When the government harms an

             individual without following established legal procedures, it constitutes a violation of due process, which

             goes against the rule of law.

          • Alternatively and controversially, due process has been interpreted as limiting laws and legal proceedings,

             allowing judges, instead of legislators, to define and guarantee fundamental fairness, justice, and liberty.]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[EXAMPLES OF DUE PROCESS OF LAW







  1. Being Informed Of Your Rights (Miranda Rights): For due process, most nations insist that people should be


        informed of their rights. If not, then due process is violated. A great example of this is Miranda rights in the USA.


  2. The Right To A Fair And Impartial Trial: In far too many nations in the world, the judiciary system is corrupted by



        politics. The executive and lawmaking branches of government instil their own puppets in the legal system so they can


        manipulate the results.


  3. The Right To An Attorney: In order for due process to be executed, most nations allow people to have an attorney



        represent them in court.


  4. The Right To Present Evidence: The right to present evidence underpins a fair legal system. It ensures that individuals


        have the opportunity to state their case and bring to the jury anything that supports their case.


  5. The Right To Cross-Examine Witnesses: While a defendant has the right to present evidence and bring witness, so too



        does the prosecutor.


  6. The Burden Of Proof: The burden of proof is perhaps the most important due process example. It refers to the


        responsibility of the party making a claim to provide evidence or proof that supports their argument.]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[CONT.








  7.      Legal Search And Seizure: Evidence obtained through an illegal search or seizure may be excluded from trial.


  The prosecutors must work hard to ensure they do everything within the law so they don’t cause a mistrial.


  8. Right To Silence: The famous fifth amendment of the US constitution states that people should not be compelled



  to give incriminating evidence against themselves.



  9.     The Right To Appeal: Even once a person is convicted, they still have due process rights. One of these is the


       right to appeal a finding.


  10. Freedom From Double Jeopardy: Double jeopardy refers to someone being prosecuted twice for the same



       crime. This is not allowed in most nations.



  11. The Right To A Speedy Trial: Many jurisdictions have laws preventing the government from holding a person


       indefinitely without a trial.


  12. The Right To Trial By Jury: People have the right to trial by jury in many nations. This helps to prevent the



       government from abusing its power by instating corrupt judges]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[2.    SPEEDY TRIALS



  • Constitution - serves as the cornerstone of justice in a democratic society; Responsible for the preservation of

      Fundamental Rights.


  • The accused in all criminal cases has the right to a speedy trial.


  • The right to a speedy trial guarantees that justice is delivered on time, avoiding excessive delays that might result

      in mental suffering and denial of justice.


  • The idea of a speedy trial has roots in ancient legal systems. For example, in ancient Rome - “Twelve Tables” -

      required cases to be resolved within a certain time;



  • In English Common Law – Magna Carta (1215) - justice should not be denied, sold, or delayed - quick

      justice and protection against unfair detention.


  • Factors leading to Pendency of Cases:

                 • Inadequate number of judges


                 • Procedural complexities


                 • Case backlog

                 • Administrative inefficiencies


                 • Prolonged investigations


                 • Hearing adjournments and delays]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Provisions for Speedy trial under Indian laws: Several provisions exist in the Criminal Procedure

  Code (CrPC) to address the issue of delay and ensure a speedy trial. Here are some of the key provisions:




  • Section 157(1) of CrPC: It mandates that upon receiving information about the commission of an offense,

       the police officer must promptly send a report to the magistrate and proceed to the scene to investigate.





  • Section 173(1) of CrPC: This provision requires the completion of all investigations under Chapter XII of

       the CrPC without unnecessary delay.




  • Section 207 of CrPC: It grants the accused the right to obtain free copies of various documents, including


       the police report, FIR, statements recorded under Section 161(3), confessions, and other documents

       submitted to the magistrate under Section 173(5).




  • Chapter XXI of CrPC (Section 260 to Section 265): This chapter provides for summary trials in certain

       petty offenses, allowing for a more expeditious resolution.




  • Section 468 of CrPC: It sets a limitation period for taking cognizance of offenses, specifying different


       timeframes based on the punishment prescribed for the offense.]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[In addition to these existing provisions, certain amendments have been made to address

  delay and expedite the trial process:





  • Section 167(2)(a) of CrPC: This provision deals with police custody, judicial custody, and default bail. It limits

        the initial police custody to 15 days and provides for the release of the accused on bail if the investigation is not

        completed within specified timeframes.




  • Section 173(1A) of CrPC: It specifically mandates the completion of investigations into offenses of rape within

        two months.




  • Chapter XXIA of CrPC (Section 265-A to Section 265-L): This chapter introduces the concept of Plea

        Bargaining, which aims to expedite the resolution of criminal charges for offenses with punishments less than

        seven years.




  • Section 309(1) of CrPC: It was inserted to prevent delays in trials and requires proceedings to be conducted on a

        day-to-day basis until the examination of all witnesses is completed. In cases of certain offenses related to sexual

        assault, the inquiry or trial should ideally be completed within two months from the filing of the charge sheet.







          These provisions and amendments reflect the legislature’s intent to address delays, protect the rights of the

                                          accused, and ensure a more efficient and expeditious trial process.]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[Case Laws on Speedy Trial



















                                                                        -Peer Teaching]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[3.    ACCESS TO JUSTICE







  • The Constitution of India has provided for Article 39A, Article 14, and Article 21 that guarantee the citizens the right to

      access to justice. Yet, access to justice as a human right remains problematic in international as well as national law.


  • The Constitution of India through Article 32and Article 226 promises to provide an effective mechanism and secure the

      fundamental right of every person to get access to courts in India.


  • These Articles are a speed track mechanism and provide quick remedies. A person has the right to directly approach the

      Supreme Court through Article 32 without having to go through the hassle of approaching lower courts.


  • The Constitution is thus the protector and assurer of our fundamental right to get access to courts.


  • Similarly, the High Courts have power through Article 226 of the Constitution that ensures that a person can approach

      the High Court for a fundamental right violation or any other matter.


  • In this regard, Article 32 is restrictive as compared to Article 226, as a person can apply Article 32 only in cases of

      fundamental rights violations


  • But through Article 226, the High Courts can be approached for any matter (matters that do not necessarily revolve

      around fundamental rights violations).


  • The Supreme Court time and again has taken progressive measures to promote access to justice and has upheld the

      Constitution that guarantees this as a fundamental right. It has done so by applying a twin strategy of loosening the

      traditional rules of locus standi and relaxing procedural rules in such cases.]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[Alternative Dispute Resolution System





  • ADRS – a/c as external dispute resolution; typically denotes a wide range of dispute resolution processes and

      techniques that act as a means for disagreeing parties to come to an agreement.


  • Litigation is a lengthy process leading to unnecessary delays in dispensation of justice as well as over-burdening

      the Judiciary.


  • Alternative Dispute Resolution (ADR) mechanisms like arbitration, conciliation and mediation etc. offer better
      and timely solution for resolution of a dispute. Generally, ADR uses neutral third party who helps the parties to

      communicate, discuss the differences and resolve the dispute.


  • It is a method which enables individuals and group to maintain co-operation, social order and provides opportunity

      to reduce hostility.


  • ADR offers to resolve all type of matters including civil, commercial, industrial and family etc., where people are
      not being able to start any type of negotiation and reach the settlement.


  • These ADR mechanisms are less adversarial and are capable of providing a an amicable outcome in comparison to

      conventional methods of resolving disputes.


  • Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 - one of the most popular modes of ADR in India - Arbitration,


  • Alternative Dispute Resolution (ADR) Mechanisms - ADR is a mechanism of dispute resolution that is non

      adversarial, i.e. working together co-operatively to reach the best resolution for everyone.]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[Types of ADR:


  1.      Arbitration

                 • The dispute is submitted to an arbitral tribunal which makes a decision (an "award") on the

                      dispute that is mostly binding on the parties.

                 • It is less formal than a trial, and the rules of evidence are often relaxed.

                 • Generally, there is no right to appeal an arbitrator's decision.

                 • Except for some interim measures, there is very little scope for judicial intervention in the


                      arbitration process.
  2.      Conciliation


                 • A non-binding procedure in which an impartial third party, the conciliator, assists the parties to a
                      dispute in reaching a mutually satisfactory agreed settlement of the dispute.

                 • Conciliation is a less formal form of arbitration.

                 • The parties are free to accept or reject the recommendations of the conciliator.


                 • However, if both parties accept the settlement document drawn by the conciliator, it shall be final
                      and binding on both.


  3. Mediation
                        • In mediation, an impartial person called a "Mediator" helps the parties try to reach a


                             mutually acceptable resolution of the dispute.
                        • The mediator does not decide the dispute but helps the parties communicate so they can try to


                             settle the dispute themselves.
                        • Mediation leaves control of the outcome with the parties.]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[3.      Negotiation

                        • A non-binding procedure in which discussions between the parties are initiated without the

                             intervention of any third party with the object of arriving at a negotiated settlement to the

                             dispute.

                        • It is the most common method of Alternative Dispute Resolution.

                        • Negotiation occurs in business, non-profit organizations, government branches, legal proceedings,

                             among nations and in personal situations such as marriage, divorce, parenting, and everyday life.

  4.      Lok Adalat

                        • An interesting feature of the Indian legal system is the existence of voluntary agencies called Lok

                             Adalat (Peoples' Courts).

                        • The Legal Services Authorities Act was passed in 1987 to encourage out-of-court settlements, and

                        • the new Arbitration and Conciliation Act was enacted in 1996.

                        • Lok Adalat or "People's Court" comprises an informal setting which facilitates negotiations in the

                             presence of a judicial officer wherein cases are dispensed without undue emphasis on legal

                             technicalities.

                        • The order of the Lok-Adalat is final and shall be deemed to be a decree of a civil court and shall be

                             binding on the parties to the dispute.

                        • The order of the Lok-Adalat is not appealable in a court of law]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[Importance of ADRS In India – Peer Study]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[RESTORATIVE JUSTICE














     • A process whereby all parties with a stake in a specific offence come together to resolve

        collectively how to deal with the aftermath of the offence and its implications for the future“



     • this system aims to put the power to decide on the people "most affected" by the crime


     • "repair" the harm caused because of the crime



     • "rehabilitation" of the offender


     • “Criminal justice system" in India is also somewhere afflicted with this problem of lack of


        effective victim involvement.


     • Although criminal procedural laws in India do not mention the principle of restorative justice,

        some provisions of such laws provides some features of it.]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[Process Of Restorative Justice

  Restorative Justice's fundamental principles are implemented in a variety of ways and models. These

  efforts are centered on "resolving" the victim's/aggrieved party's harm, involving "all parties affected by

  the crime or civil wrong", "empowering victims", and "facilitating dialogue among various

  stakeholders".





  Dialogue Between Victim & Offender:

  It is one of the best ways to show how restorative justice works, and it has gotten a lot of attention around

  the world. A trained mediator helps the "victim" and the "offender" meet face-to-face in order to come

  up with a plan to repair any damage caused by the crime or civil wrong that happened.




  Conferencing:

  Conferencing refers to the discussions in which the victim and offender reach an agreement on redress,


  which may include financial restitution, symbolic restitution tailored to the victim's needs, "community

  service", "offender therapy", or any other agreed-upon undertaking to repair the victim's harm caused

  by the offender

  Forming Restorative Circle:

  Restorative circles bring stakeholders together to communicate and listen to one another.Participants

  should form a circle and give each person an equal opportunity to speak during the discussion. In these

  Circles, individuals can discuss the impact of the crime/civil wrong on the victim, their families, and the


  community, as well as the restitution for the same.]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[Restorative Justice in India



  •       Panchayat System




  •       Lok Adalat



  •       Arbitration and Conciliation




  •       Under the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection) Act 2015






  Restorative Justice In Indian Criminal Procedural Law:



  The Code of Criminal Procedure 1973 has some rules that are based on restorative justice. Because of this, the


  victim and the people who harmed her are encouraged to come to an agreement. Among the important rules:



  •       Plea Bargaining



  •       Compoundable offence




  •       Compensation



  •       Probation]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[UNIT 4
















                LAW OF EVIDENCE AND MINOR ACTS]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[INTRODUCTION














     • The Indian Evidence Act of 1872 is a crucial piece of legislation that regulates


        the admissibility, relevancy, and trustworthiness of evidence submitted in Indian


        courts.



     • The Act came into effect on September 1, 1872, and has played an important


        part in moulding the Indian judicial system since then.



     • The Act was passed to guarantee a fair trial and to bar untrustworthy evidence


        from being considered by the court.



     • The Act governs all court processes in India, both civil and criminal.



     • It establishes the rules and principles governing evidence admissibility, the


        standard of proof, and the weight to be given to evidence submitted in court.]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[The entire corpus juris (body of laws) is divided into two broad categories:



  • Substantiative



  • Procedural



  • The law of evidence does not fall under substantive or procedural law, but rather under the ‘adjective



       law,’ which describes the pleading and method by which substantive laws are put into operation.



  • In litigation, the opposing parties produce proof to disprove each other’s allegations. In legal systems,



       the law of evidence governs this sphere.


  • Applies to both civil and criminal law; is a prerequisite for any criminal or civil trial;




  • Role of IEA is to scientifically reconstruct the past events on which the disputing parties disagree.


  • The goal of evidence law is to seek the truth and to be an effective tool in the fact-finding process.



  • The law of evidence has established two fundamental concepts, i) relevancy, and ii) admissibility.]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[Elements of the Indian Evidence Act



  The Indian Evidence Act is divided into three parts-



  •The first part deals with the general rules of evidence.


  •The second part deals with the relevancy of facts.



  •The third part deals with the production and effect of evidence.










  General Rules of Evidence



  • The first section of the Act lays out the basic evidence guidelines that must be observed in all judicial proceedings.



  • The guidelines cover witness competency, the weight of evidence, and the assumption of innocence.



  • The Act also specifies the circumstances under which a person may be forced to testify in court and the penalties


        for neglecting to do so.]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[Relevancy of Facts


  • The second section of the Act addresses the relevance of data.



  • It specifies which details are pertinent to a case and which are not.


  • The Act specifies the circumstances in which a truth can be deemed relevant and how it must be proven in court.



  • It also addresses the validity of hearsay evidence, expert testimony, and prior judgements.











  Production and Effect of Evidence



  • The third section of the Act addresses the generation and application of proof.



  • It specifies the guidelines for providing evidence in court as well as the weight to be assigned to various kinds of


        evidence.


  • The Act also addresses document validity and the guidelines for demonstrating their legitimacy.]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[Significance of the Indian Evidence Act


  • The Indian Evidence Act is important for a number of reasons.



                        1.     It guarantees that only credible and admissible proof is given in court, thereby improving the quality


                               of justice.



                        2.     It protects the rights of witnesses and accused by defining the circumstances under which they can


                               be forced to testify.



                        3.     By establishing clear guidelines for the production and impact of evidence, it serves to avoid abuse


                               of judicial procedures.



                        4.     It is a critical instrument for assuring the Indian legal system’s justice and neutrality.]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[Definition of evidence under the Indian Evidence Act



  As per Section 3 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872



   ‘Evidence’ means and includes the following:


  • All statements made before the Court by witnesses about matters of fact under investigation, which the Court


        permits or requires; such statements are referred to as oral evidence;



  • All documents (including electronic records) presented for the inspection of the Court; such materials are referred



        to as documentary evidence.




  • In the case of Kalyan Kumar Gogoi v. Ashutosh Agnihotri and Anr, AIR 2011


  The Supreme Court made the following observations on evidence, the word ‘evidence’ has been used in common



  parlance in three different senses: as



  1. Equivalent to relevant,


  2. As equivalent to proof, and


  3.As equivalent to the material, based on which Courts conclude the existence or non-existence of disputed facts.]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>